The 52nd General Hospital Collection
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The 52nd General Hospital Collection
1917-2009
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Various and unknown
5.33 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of the World War II 52nd General Hospital, which was affiliated with Syracuse University College of Medicine and stationed at Camp Livingston, Louisiana and Kidderminster, England. The collection has five series: Photographs, Audio-Visual Materials, Memorabilia, Printed Materials, and Subject Files.
FIC2017.0009. Also see call numbers 1997.0003, 1997.0004, 2002.0003, 2008.0003, 2008.0004, 2009.0002, and 2011.0002.
Historical Note
In 1922, the Syracuse University College of Medicine was authorized to organize and staff the 52nd General Hospital. It was organized in 1941 during World War II and called to active duty on September 1st, 1942 for basic training at Camp Livingston, Louisiana. The unit was then briefly transferred to Camp Kilmer near Brunswick, New Jersey before embarking on January 2nd, 1943 on the Queen Elizabeth with 18,000 troops. On January 8th, it disembarked at Grenoch and was taken by train to Taunton, England. It remained at Camp Norton until March 1st, when they were transferred to the permanent hospital at Wolverley, near Kidderminster, England. The unit treated casualties from the D-Day invasions and the Battle of the Bulge and was most active during its last year and a half before its dissolution on June 14th, 1945.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of the World War II 52nd General Hospital, which was affiliated with Syracuse University College of Medicine and stationed at Camp Livingston, Louisiana and Kidderminster, England. There are five series in this collection.
Photographs: these materials include negatives and print photographs of the 52nd GH donated by various individuals. Almost every photograph has been digitized and can be viewed on the Archives and Special Collections METS database or on the New York Heritage and Digital Public Library of America websites.
Memorabilia: this series contains oversize certificate and poster memorabilia from the unit.
Printed Materials: these documents include printed materials about the unit, including newsletters, newspaper clippings, emails, transcriptions, and published maps and articles.
Subject Files: this series has various sub-series of individuals and events relating to the 52nd GH in a variety of formats, including photographs; writings, such as correspondence, notes, and diaries; ephemera that is loose and mounted in scrapbooks; audio-visual materials; and printed materials, such as publications, newsletters, photocopies of federal records, newspaper clippings, and extensive original documentation on the camp from Dr. Farr.
Audio-Visual Materials: these materials include various audio-visual materials from the 52nd GH, including CD, VHS, DVD, cassette, 78rpm vinyl, and 16mm film recordings.
Arrangement of the Collection
The 52nd General Hospital Collection has been arranged into five series.
Separated Material
Several items have been removed to the objects collection, including a WWII Japanese gas mask kit and leather army field medical kit from Kenneth W. Wright, the flag used in the 2008 memorial dedication ceremony, and a plaque in honor of the University Hospital of the Good Shepherd staff who served in the military. Some names are missing from this plaque, but the remaining ones are: Dr. E.G. Allen, Dr. J.B. Alsever, Dr. W.D. Alsever, Dr. A.U. Acuilino, Dr. W.D. Ayer, Dr. C.O. Barney, Dr. L.G. Berman, Dr. S.C. Bregande, Dr. S.A. Britten, Dr. J.C.M. Brust, Dr. T.L. Bryant, Dr. G.T. Church, Dr. J.E. Delmonico, Dr. Ecker, Dr. R.D. Fairchild, Dr. R.S. Farr, Dr. R.C. Farrow, Dr. L.G. Fournier, Dr. C. Geiger, Dr. R.O. Gregg, Dr. A.E. Harris, Dr. G.D. Hoople, Dr. H.C. Kroon, Dr. Max Kutzer, Dr. P.H. Lowry, Dr. J.R. Myers, Dr. [J.]W. Pennock, Dr. A.B. Raffl, Dr. P.H. Rakov, Dr. C.D. Reid, Dr. [Rubenstein], Dr. D.B. Sanford, Dr. F.J. Schoeneck, Dr. P.W. Smith, Dr. J.B. Stevens, Dr. S.W. Stringer, Dr. Irving [?]. In addition, the books Song and Service Book for Ship and Field: Army and Navy. New York: A.S. Barnes and Company, 1942 and Manual for the Medical Department United States Army 1916 were removed to the rare books collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Anthony, Eugene W. c. 1914-2006; Ayer, Wardner D.; Berman, Leon G. 1909-1971; Ecker, Arthur David 1913-2006; Farr, Richard S. 1890-1977; Johnson, Winifred P. 1919-2006; Rowlingson, John C.; Wright, Kenneth W. 1912-2003; Camp Livingston (La.); Kidderminster (England); Syracuse University, College of Medicine; United States. Army. General Hospital, 52nd; Wolverley (Herefordshire, England); World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--England; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Various and unknown. Also see call numbers 1997.0003, 1997.0004, 2002.0003, 2008.0003, 2008.0004, 2009.0002, and 2011.0002.
Inventory
- Photographs
  - Rowlingson, Brewer, and unknown donations. All photographs have been digitized and can be found on the New York Heritage website., 1942-1945; 2005; 2 boxes and 1 folder (Box Boxes 1, 2, and 3)
  - Photographs and correspondence from George D. Lynch to Max Kutzer. All photographs have been digitized and can be found on the New York Heritage website., 1942-1944; 1996 (Box Box 3)
  - undated (Box Box 3)
  - Negatives of England maps and the Massage and X-Ray Wing from Foster C. Rulison., 1946 (Box Box 3)
  - c. 1942 (Box Box 3)
  - Photographs from Klett taken in the Wolverley area., 1996 (Box Box 3)
  - Photocopies of group photographs of the unit., undated (Box Box 3)
  - Mounted photographs, postcard descriptions, summary of the unit, and prisoner of war and family accounts from England and Louisiana compiled by Wardner D. Ayer., 1942-1944; 1949 (Box Box 3)
  - 1942-1943 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
- Memorabilia
  - undated (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Poster for the 1st Anniversary Dance of the 52nd in the ETO., c. 1944 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certificate from the Medical Department Army of the United States for Syracuse University to organize the 52nd general hospital., 1922 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
- Printed Materials
  - Special Map A of Georgia with Protractors printed by the ROTC., 1935 (Box Box 3)
  - Transcriptions of oral histories and articles, information, and emails on the camp from Mike Webster., 2001; 2005-2007; undated (Box Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings., 1942-1945; 1950; 2007-2008 (Box Box 3)
  - Elizabethan News newsletter, series 10, no.1-5. Preservation photocopies in previous clippings folder., 1943 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Wartime in Wyre Forest publication with Wolverley US Army Hospital article., 2010 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
- Subject Files
  - Leon G. Berman
    - Ephemera: souvenir program for “Skirts” musical by US 8th Air Force; program for Dr. Malcolm Sargent and the Liverpool Philharmonic Orchestra performance in Birmingham; program for piano recital by Lieutenant Edward Kilenyi; and newspaper photograph of nurses from Syracuse hospitals leaving with the medical unit., 1944 (Box Box 3)
    - 1942, 1952; undated (Box Box 3)
    - Research notes, obituary, and correspondence excerpts on Leon G. Berman and the 52nd General Hospital from Paul Berman., 1971; 2002; 2009 (Box Box 3)
    - Photocopies of documents from the National Archives and Records Administration on the 52nd General Hospital., undated; 2 folders (Box Box 4)
  - Richard S. Farr
    - Business cards, newspaper clippings and obituary, negative of portrait photograph of Dr. Farr, and brochures for Orthopedic Teaching Laboratory, Gait Analysis, and Zimmer Reduction Retention Apparatus., 1977; undated (Box Box 4)
    - Publications and 52nd documentation, including rosters, reports, telegraphs, certificates, correspondence, orders, and pay and allowance accounts., 1938-1945 (Box Box 4)
    - Lecture and medical notes., 1938-1939 (Box Box 4)
    - Assignments of officers at Camp Livingston in Louisiana., 1942 (Box Box 4)
    - Receipts from England., 1943-1944 (Box Box 4)
    - Travel maps and brochures, memos, ophthalmology reports, Easter service program, and group photographs of the 52nd., 1942-1945 (Box Box 4)
    - Printed questions for oral answer for 2nd sitting day and typed “To the Class of 1943-Those famous juniors of a year ago” by Lt. Col. Wardner D. Ayer. (Box Box 4)
    - Standard Terms for Diagnosis, coding instructions (numerical code for records or punch cards), and coding for diseases., 1943 (Box Box 4)
    - Correspondence with Dixie and daughter Sally., 1942; 1945 (Box Box 4)
    - List of cash expenditures, hospital regulations the 52nd general hospital A.P.O. 651, personal correspondence, physical examinations and communications concerning physicals, receipted invoices, and instructions for movement., 1940-1945 (Box Box 5)
    - Ephemera, including invitations, daily bulletins, greeting cards, and notes., 1943-1944 (Box Box 5)
    - Registrar’s file, including procedure for admission of patients at 52nd general hospital; discharge procedure; procedures for evacuation of boarded patients; procedure for reception and evacuation of battle casualties; photocopy of battle casualties after D Day; Circular #37 “Records and Reports for Sick and Wounded”; instructions and administrative forms from Ward Office., 1943-1945 (Box Box 5)
    - Promotion of officers, orders, and Camp Livingston assignments and lists of officers and men., 1942-1943; 1945 (Box Box 5)
    - “Miscellaneous” items, including “Table of Organization” pamphlet, admissions and discharges statistics, correspondence, ETO medical society program, and information on visits and beds., 1943-1945 (Box Box 5)
    - Orthopedic staffs and consultants at UK Base Hospitals and Dr. Farr’s evaluation of orthopedic staffs., 1944-1945 (Box Box 5)
    - Syracuse newspapers from Victory in Europe Day, the end of World War II, and Franklin Delano Roosevelt’s death., 1945 (Box Box 5)
    - Admissions and discharges charts., 1943-1945; 2 boxes (Box Boxes 9 and 10)
  - Kenneth W. Wright
    - Administrative manual for the coordination and integration of activities relative to hospital release procedures in Onondaga county prepared by Division of Patient Services, Kenneth W. Wright and Francis X. McCann., 1969 (Box Box 5)
    - For use in my public health lecture syllabus: paper on ethics by Kenneth W. Wright., undated (Box Box 5)
    - Partial list of newspaper clippings, presentations, official pronouncements, article on Ray Brook State Tuberculosis Hospital, and photograph from Kenneth W. Wright., 1949; 1954; 1970-1976; 1983; 1990; 1996 (Box Box 5)
    - Problems of primary care: material for syllabus for K.W. Wright’s talks., 1981-1983; undated (Box Box 5)
    - Unpublished paper by Fred Beck and Kenneth Wright having to do with the Herman M. Biggs Memorial Tuberculosis Hospital., undated (Box Box 6)
    - Yank Magazine, Tokyo Edition, October 12, 1945, v.1, no.3 and November 30, 1945, v.1, no.10 and British edition, May 19, 1945, v.3, no.48; clippings from 1945 on divine wind and kamikaze, Pullman Car Company advertisement, Princess Elizabeth, Cyclone Division and Bataan, Hiroshima and Nagasaki, US Army Units shoulder insignia; The Sunday Cloner from July 29, 1945; Life article, “U.S. Occupies Japan”; and from Yank, The Army Weekly, “Yanks in the Far East.”, undated (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
    - Scrapbook created by Lois Wright with newspaper clippings, hotel receipts, church programs, photographs and brochures from Louisiana, Caduceus: The Voice of the Medical Battalion newsletter, drawings, clothing patches, Army Song Book, reference guide to military insignia, Cycloner newsletters from Camp Livingston in Louisiana, copies of photographs of Kenneth W. Wright and his wife Lois Wright, and correspondence between Kenneth W. Wright and his family, including telegrams, World War II postcards, greeting cards, envelopes, and letters., 1941-1945 (Box Box 12, Oversize shelving)
    - Biographical Vignettes from foundations well and truly laid the early history of SUNY health science center at Syracuse by Kenneth W. Wright., 1994-1996; undated (Box Box 14)
    - Two draft manuscript copies and sourcebook for second edition of "foundations well and truly laid a history of the state university of New York health science center at Syracuse” and "from teaching college to research university: the first hundred years of the SUNY health science center at Syracuse University college of medicine, 1834-1934" with photograph of Kenneth Wright and Millie Ashmore RN., c. 1964; 1996-1998; 2000-2001; 2 folders (Box Box 14)
  - John Rowlingson
    - Dr. Rowlingson notes and photocopies., undated (Box Box 6)
    - Ephemera and maps from the March of the XX Corps, golf courses, postcards, a dinner, a theater, a dance at Bewdley, baseball at Halesowen, and the 93rd bomb group travelling circus celebration of the completion of 391 bombing missions by the 8th air force., 1943-1945; undated (Box Box 6)
  - Eugene W. Anthony
    - Two photographs and photocopies of correspondence and publications., c. 1942; undated (Box Box 6)
  - Arthur D. Ecker
    - ETO medical society program, correspondence and information on 52nd reunion, and photocopies of clippings, travel orders, and notes., 1943; 1967; undated (Box Box 6)
  - Wardner D. Ayer
    - Scrapbook made by Dr. Ayer with newspaper clippings, correspondence, and reports., 1920-1942 (Box Box 12, Oversize shelving)
    - Scrapbook made by Dr. Ayer with newspaper clippings, postcards, telegrams, theater programs, photographs of family and England, and correspondence., 1935-1950 (Box Box 11, Oversize shelving)
    - Transcription of Dr. Ayer’s correspondence received from Dr. Kenneth Wright., 1991 (Box Box 6)
    - Kenneth W. Wright’s two student notebooks for Wardner D. Ayer’s neuropathology and neurology courses with lectures, case presentations, pathology findings, illustrations and drawings, photographs, publications, notes, test questions, and Dr. Ayer’s epilogue last lecture before departing for World War II service., 1937; 1942; 2 folders (Box Boxes 13 and 14)
    - Photocopies of Dr. Ayer’s obituary., undated (Box Box 13)
    - Information and lists of glass lantern slides from Dr. Ayer., 1969-1970; undated (Box Box 13)
  - Winifred P. Johnson
    - Nurse Winifred P. Johnson’s wartime diary in four volumes., 1942-1944; 2 folders (Box Box 6)
    - Partial transcription of wartime diary by Barbara L. Harris., undated (Box Box 6)
  - Brewer, Ecker, and Kutzer Health Sciences Library Lecture, Slides, Photographs, Exhibit, and Publication “Syracuse College of Medicine in World War II” and "Medical Contributions of the 52nd to the European Campaign" in the SUNY HSC/Syracuse Medical Alumni Association Alumni Journal.
    - 1996-1997 (Box Box 6)
  - 2003 Jo Grant BBC report
    - Correspondence, press releases, notes, and photocopies of newspaper clippings on Jo Grant being the BBC Midland Today’s Young Reporter of the Year., 2002-2003 (Box Box 6)
    - CD recording of A Brief History of Wolverley Camp narrated by Jo Grant from Wolverley Camp Archives., c. 2003 (Box Box 6)
    - VHS recording of Wolverley Village 1944 US Army Camp by Jo Grant for the BBC Midlands Today report., 2003 (Box Box 7)
  - 2008 memorial dedication
    - DVD recording of “Somewhere in England: The dedication of a memorial to the 52nd General Hospital at St. Johns Church, Wolverley on 29 June 2008.” (Box Box 7)
    - Copies of photographs from the ceremony., 2008 (Box Box 7)
    - Brochures, correspondence, newspaper articles, donors, sponsors, and guest list for the ceremony., 2007-2008 (Box Box 7)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  - CD recording of photographs and audio recordings from the SUNY Upstate Archives and audio recordings by Barbara Harris RN PhD with Vince Steele, Alice Reynolds, Max Kutzer, and Winifred Paul Johnson., undated (Box Box 7)
  - VHS recording copy of 16mm film by Lieutenant Colonel Richard S. Farr for Brewer., undated (Box Box 7)
  - Cassette recording copy by Belfer archive from the 78rpm vinyl single sided 12 inch discs., 1996 (Box Box 7)
  - Cassette recording of interview with Max Kutzer by Barbara Harris with transcription., 2005 (Box Box 8)
  - Cassette recording on the 52nd general hospital., 1996 (Box Box 8)
  - 16mm film of 52nd general hospital by Lieutenant Colonel Richard S. Farr for Brewer., 1944 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence on and 2 DVD recordings of “Wolverley Camp: The Story.”, 2004 (Box Box 8)
  - 78rpm vinyl single sided 12 inch discs from US General Hospital WSYR and BBC on August 21, 1943 that includes Lieutenant Colonel Richard Farr, Captain Ivy Wadsworth Sergeant Thomas Wagoner and many names of Syracusans stationed at hospital. Broadcast was underwritten by Herman G. Weiskotten for $25,000 in war bonds and narrated by Art Feldman. (Box Box 11, Oversize shelving)